<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fruiterers secrets Containing directions, for the due time, and manner, of gathering all kindes of fruite, aswell stone-fruite as other: and how they are afterwards to be ordered in packing, carrying and conueighing them by land or by water; then in separating or culling them into diuers sorts; and lastly, in resruing or laying them vp, so, as may bee for their best lasting and continuance. Enterlaced with diuerse other secrets (and their naturall causes) touching trees, and their fruite. No treatise, to this purpose, being heretofore published.</title>
            <author>N. F., fl. 1604.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00515</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10650</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103478</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839231</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839231</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3634</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00515)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3634)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1023:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fruiterers secrets Containing directions, for the due time, and manner, of gathering all kindes of fruite, aswell stone-fruite as other: and how they are afterwards to be ordered in packing, carrying and conueighing them by land or by water; then in separating or culling them into diuers sorts; and lastly, in resruing or laying them vp, so, as may bee for their best lasting and continuance. Enterlaced with diuerse other secrets (and their naturall causes) touching trees, and their fruite. No treatise, to this purpose, being heretofore published.</title>
                  <author>N. F., fl. 1604.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. B[radocke]and are to be solde by Roger Iackson, at his shop in Fleete-streete, neere the conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The epistle to the reader" signed: N.F.</note>
                  <note>Title page verso has dedication to Charles [Blount,] Earl of Devonshire.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fruit --  England --  Harvesting --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fruit --  Transportation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fruit --  Storage --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3634:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3634:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FRVITERERS SECRETS: Containing directions, for the due time, and manner, of gathering all kindes of fruite, aſwell ſtone-fruite as other: and how they are afterwards to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in packing, carrying and conueighing them by land or by water; then in ſeparating or culling them into diuers ſorts; and laſtly, in reſeruing or laying them vp, ſo, as may bee for their beſt laſting and continuance.</p>
            <p>Enterlaced with diuerſe other ſecrets (and their naturall cauſes) touching trees, and their fruite.</p>
            <p>No Treatiſe, to this purpoſe, being here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore publiſhed.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by R.B. and are to be ſolde by <hi>Roger Iackſon,</hi> at his ſhop in Fleete-ſtreete, neere the conduit. 1604.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3634:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the right honorable,</hi> Charles, <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Deuonſhire,</hi> Lo: <hi>Mountioye,</hi> Lo: Lieutenant of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and one of his Maieſties moſt honorable Priuie Councell; <hi>N. F.</hi> wiſheth long life, with increaſe of honour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable, hauing (long ſince) often weighed and conſidered, with my ſelfe, the great care &amp; paines that haue been taken, in ſetting forth ſundry neceſſary books for plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting &amp; grafting of fruit, &amp; finding it (by much experience) no leſſe needfull, that the right order, in gatheting &amp; keeping thereof, ſhould be made knowen, &amp; obſerued: I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, at length (for the general good of the whole kingdome) to lay downe, in this ſmall Treatiſe, the diſorder and abuſes of the vnskilful in this kinde; together with the true &amp; due courſe to be taken therein. The worke now finiſhed, I haue preſumed (though far vnworthy) to publiſh it, to the world (vnder the ſhadow of your honorable protection) as the firſt fruites of a willing minde, ready to make tender of his humble ſeruice, &amp; acknowledgement of all duty, to your Lordſhip, to performe it, in what he may. Not doubting, but that, as your Ho: (next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Maieſtie) hath been the protectour &amp; preſeruer of the whole realme of <hi>Ireland,</hi> you will alſo vouchſafe to patronize and protect one Iriſh-borne, who (by long experience) hath made triall of that which he deliuereth to others. Wherefore, humbly crauing, that your Honour will bee pleaſed to accept hereof, &amp; to giue it countenance (that ſo the rather it may haue free paſſage, in deſpite of malitious &amp; ſcornfull tongues, into the hands of all ſuch as deſire to eat the fruite of their owne vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyards, in their due ſeaſon): I conclude with my earneſt and feruent prayers to Almighty God, for the protection and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of your good Lordſhip, in all true honour &amp; happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, in this life; &amp; hereafter to make you partaker of that inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable &amp; incorruptible fruit of the life eternall, which groweth not in orchards of mens planting, but in the Paradiſe of God,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Nouember, the</hi> 7.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Honours, in all humbleneſſe, <hi>N. F.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3634:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, as there haue been diuers bookes ſet forth for the good of this land, and the great encreaſe of fruite; As of planting, ſetting, proy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and grafting, alſo of preſeruing them, after the order of the Apothecary: ſo amongſt the reſt, beſtowe the Reading of this little worke; wherein you ſhall finde the true order of gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, carrying, and keeping of all ſorts of fruites, in their ſeaſon, and how you ſhall know what time your ſeuerall fruites are ready to be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered; eſpecially all kinde of pippins, and apples, all kinde of peares, wardens, Quinces, and Medlers, alſo cherries and other ſtone fruite whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>I omit the nominating of all kind of fruites; for they be too many to be ſeuerally named. And commonly euery fruite country hath their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall names, although one kinde of fruite. As, Iohn-apples be, in ſome places, called Dewzings or long-laſters: and Gooddings be called old Wiues, &amp;c. Yet although not ſeuerally named, you ſhall by this Treatiſe know the due courſe how to gather all kindes in their prime and ſeaſon, and afterwards to carry or conueigh them, either by land or by water, and then how to reſerue or keep them, to endure longeſt. And, afore I proceede to the Treatiſe it ſelfe, I thinke meete to acquaint thee from whence our great plentie of fruite, in <hi>England,</hi> came.</p>
            <p>One <hi>Richard Harris</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> borne in <hi>Ireland,</hi> Fruiterer to King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, fetched out of <hi>Fraunce</hi> great ſtore of grafies, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally pippins: before which time there was no right pippins in <hi>England.</hi> He fetched alſo, out of the Lowe Countries, Cherrie grafts, &amp; Peare grafts, of diuers ſorts: Then tooke a peece of ground belonging to the King, in the parriſh of <hi>Tenham</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> being about the quantitie of ſeauen ſcore acres; whereof he made an Orchard, planting therein all thoſe foraigne grafts. Which Orchard is, and hath been from time to time, the chiefe Mother of all other orchards for thoſe kindes
<pb facs="tcp:3634:3"/>of fruites in <hi>Kent,</hi> and of diuers other places. And afore that theſe ſaid grafts were fetched out of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and the Lowe Countries, although that there was ſome ſtore of fruite in <hi>England,</hi> yet there wanted both rare fruite, and laſting fine fruite. The Dutch &amp; French, finding it to be ſo ſcarce, eſpecially in theſe countries neere <hi>London,</hi> commonly plyed <hi>Billings-gate,</hi> &amp; diuers other places with ſuch kinde of fruite. But now (thankes bee to God) diuers Gentlemen &amp; others, taking delight in grafting (being a matter ſo neceſſary and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial in a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth) haue planted many Orchards; fetching their grafts out of that Orchard, which <hi>Harris</hi> planted called the <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garden.</hi> And by reaſon of the great increaſe that now is growing in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers parts of this Land, of ſuch fine &amp; ſeruiceable fruit, there is no need of any foraigne fruite, but we are able to ſerue other places.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, ſince it hath pleaſed Almighty God, to giue encreaſe &amp; plenty of fruite in this land, and that diuers haue taken paines in the maintenance thereof, of all degrees: (the better ſort for their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, &amp; in that they doe delight to ſee the worke of their owne handes proſper, as alſo to eate the fruite thereof; the common ſort, for profit, and for the better reliefe of their family) In regard, I ſay, of the great paines that haue been taken, in planting, ſetting, grafting, &amp; proyning, whereby a great deale of ground hath been taken vp, which might ſerue for other good purpoſes; I thought good to ſhew what courſe might bee taken, that mens Labours be not loſt, nor ſuch great quantity of grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, wherein fruite doth growe, lye in waſte (as it were) and become vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, through ignorance of well handling the fruite, after God hath giuen it.</p>
            <p>For if there be not as great care taken for the well gathering, and good vſage of fruite, as hath been for the planting thereof, I account moſt of the labour in planting loſt, and the grounds wherein they growe to lye partly waſte, and better to be vſed for ſome other good purpoſe. But, the fruite being well handled &amp; vſed, the ground can bee turned to no better profit. And ſo (committing both thy endeuours, and theſe my labours, to the bleſſing of God) I haſten to the Directions them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy well-willer, <hi>N.F.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3634:3"/>
            <head>THE FRVITERERS SECRETS.</head>
            <div n="cherries" type="fruit">
               <head>Of Cherries.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Herries are the firſt fruite that are to be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, eſpecially which here ſhalbe mentioned: Of which fruite there are foure ſorts here in <hi>England,</hi> (that is to ſay) Flemiſh cherries, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh cherries, Gaſcoyne cherries, and blacke cherries, whereof two are chiefly to be mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that is the Flemiſh and the Engliſh.</p>
               <p>The Flemiſh cherries are not ſo called, in reſpect that they growe in <hi>Flaunders,</hi> but that the firſt grafts and chiefe original of them came from <hi>Flaunders,</hi> and therefore they are called Flemiſh cherries: and in what place ſoeuer in England theſe graftes be, or any trees growing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3634:4"/>from them, from time to time ſince the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of them, they are ſooner ripe then they that are naturally of themſelues Engliſh Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, in ſome places foureteene daies ſooner, in other ſome three weekes, according to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes or backwardnes of the grownds wherin they grow: But wherſoeuer they grow, although in one plot or acre of grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, you ſhall yet find that the one will be ripe before the other cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge their cullor red. And as ſoone as you ſee your Cheries to change their color, &amp; be red (that is, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they beginto ripen) you muſt haue a care that you ſet one to keep the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the birds, which wil be very buſie about them, &amp; eſpecially at the breake of day, vntill eight of the clocke in the forenoone: and ſo likewiſe when the heate of the day is paſt, beginning at foure or fiue of the clocke vntill nine at night: The keeper muſt with a peece ſhoote, or make ſome other noiſe, to feare the birds, or with a ſling to throw at them, being carefull to watch at thoſe times. There are two kindes of birds eſpecially, that hurt che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries moſt: the one is called a Iay: which muſt be narrowly looked vnto, or els ſhe will pick the cheries as faſt as they ripen. The other, which is called a Bulfinch, will eate ſtones and all: but you ſhall heare her chirpe before ſhe lights vpon the tree.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The order of gathering of Cheries.</head>
                  <p>NOw for the gathering of your cheries (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all cheries vpon a tree cannot be ripe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3634:4"/>and ready to be gathered at one time) prouide a fine light ladder: &amp; looking about your tree, wher you ſee moſt ſtore ripe, there ſet it vp. Be careful for placing thereof, for feare of breaking any boughes. Alſo you muſt haue a fine hooke in your hand called a gathering hooke, to pull the bough tenderly vnto you, which you cannot reach with your hand.</p>
                  <p>You muſt prouide you alſo a chery pot or kib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zey to gather your cheries in: and to the ſame cherie pot there muſt be tyed with a ſtring a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle hooke, that when the gatherer ſets to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he may hang his chery pot vpon and bough neer, as occaſion ſerues, and ſo to be remoued at his pleaſure: Alwaies prouided, that the gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer haue a great care that he pull no more but the very ſame ſtalke that the chery hangs by: for the next knot, or brut to the ſtalke, is it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly that yeelds fruite, the yeare next enſuing.</p>
                  <p>At the gathering of your cheries there uniſt be great heede taken that they be not roughlie handled: onely pull them off by the ſtalke and lay them into your pot. For much handling of them (being a very tender fruite) will make them change their colour, and turne blackiſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ How to carry and conuey Cheries.</head>
                  <p>IF there be any great ſtore of cheries that muſt be caryed any farre way, from whence they be gathered, there muſt be prouided eyther fine baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets or ſiues: into which (when the chery pots be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3634:5"/>full, you muſt poure them out. Each of theſe ſiues ſhould haue two laths in the bottome on the outſide, not croſt, but both one way: each lath muſt be about the breadth of two fingers: and about the breadth of the palme of a mans hand betwixt, or ſomewhat more aſunder. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why I wiſh theſe laths to be vſed in the bottome, is, becauſe that when they be caryed vpon ones head, the ſiue being weake bottomed of it ſelfe, the carryers head will make a dent therein, the breadth of his head, which wold cauſe the cheryes, in all that circle of his head, to breake and to be bruſed: but the two laths will keepe his head from ſpoyling of the cheryes, and ſo to be eaſily carryed, hauing a wreath or ſome ſuch thing betwixt him and the laths, for hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his head.</p>
                  <p>The French men commonly vſe to carry their cherries in the very ſame pots that they gather them in, &amp; neuer put them out vntill ſuch times as they are to be ſpent. The Dutchmen doe turne them out of their cherry pots, into deepe rod-baſkets. This latter way is not ſo good. For, lying ſo thick one vpon another, it quickly bringeth them into a heat: and once being in a heat, they preſently rot.</p>
                  <p>But the Fruiterers of <hi>London</hi> (whoſe way I holde to be the beſt) doe firſt gather them into kibſeis, or little open baſkets: and by reaſon of their great quantity they poure them out gently into their ſiues, or broad baſkets made ſiue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion: ſo filling them that the ſiues or baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3634:5"/>may be three inches (or there about) emptie at the top. For when they be put into a Ship, Hoy, or boate, they are often (for want of roome) ſet one vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another: which would hurt the cherries, if the ſiue or baſket were full.</p>
                  <p>But otherwiſe, they that haue no great ſtore to carry or conueigh by land, may conueigh them on horſebacke in a payre of panniers, on each ſide one, lyned thinne both in the bottom and top with freſh fearn. Prouided, that your panniers or baſkets be full: or els the fruite will be ſpoiled with toſſing.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="other stone fruit" type="fruit">
               <head>¶ The order of gathering all other ſtone-fruite.</head>
               <p>COncerning Apricocks, Peaches, Peare-plums, Damſons, bullaſe, &amp;c. for the knowledge of ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of them, they are al much of a nature or qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. For although, in each kinde of them, ſome ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſooner then other ſome, euen vpon one and the ſame tree, yet as ſoone as they are ready to bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, ſome wil drop off, and the reſt remaine hard: yet then are thoſe hard ones alſo in their full tune to be gathered. Then muſt you place your ladder as before is mentioned, hauing a ſpeciall care that you hurt not the tree: alſo obſeruing that it be dry weather, and the morning deaw paſt. For, being ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered wet, they wil both looſe their perfect colour, and become mildewed. Then take your kibſey (ſuch as hath been ſhewed how to gather cherries with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all) and taking alſo a hooke in your hand to pull thoſe boughes that you cannot reach, haue ready by you a ſiue, baſket or ſome ſuch thing, that when
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3634:6"/>your kibſey is full, you may poure them thereinto. In the bottom wherof, lay nettles newly gathered, and with the like couer them on the top: which will haſten the ripening of them, make them keepe their colour, and cauſe them to eate as kindly as if they had been fully ripened vpon the tree.</p>
               <p>But if you let them hang vpon the tree vntil they be full ripe, they will drop off, for the moſt part: and the reſt that hang, will quickly rot after that they be gathered, and doe little ſeruice, except they bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently vſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="pears" type="fruit">
               <head>Three things to be conſidered, in gathering of Peares.</head>
               <p>THere are diuers wayes to bee vſed in gathering of Peares: as followeth. Firſt, it is to be noted whether they grow in a yard, garden, or backe ſide, being no more then will ſerue for a mans owne ſpending. Secondlie, whether there bee any ſuch that will be ſolde, and ſo to be conueighed any farre way, eyther by land or water. Thirdly, whether they be Peares that will ſerue for the Apothecary to preſerue, and ſo to be gathered accordingly.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How to know whether Peares be ready to be gathered.</head>
                  <p>NOw, for the gathering of ſuch as be for a mans owne vſe, no doubt but euery man hauing ſeene the naturall ripening of his owne fruite, by long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience knoweth their time of gathering: but for the better inſtruction of thoſe that newly come vnto a place, being not acquainted with the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3634:6"/>ripening of the Peares therein growing, I wil here after expreſſe how you ſhall know when their due time of gathering is.</p>
                  <p>Some, or rather moſt men, vſe not to gather their Peares vntill they be all ready to drop off: and, hanging ſo long vpon the tree, aſſoone as they be gathered, and layed one vpon another, they will be in a great heate, and preſently rot. But if you haue Peares that you make any account of, that are ſummer Peares, and for your owne vſe, aſſoone as you ſee them turne their colour, or any part of them ripe (which wil not be al at one time, although growing vpon one tree, &amp; of one ſort) ſtill gather the ripeſt, &amp; ſo by degrees at your pleaſure.</p>
                  <p>But, being gathered when they be almoſt ripe (that is, when onely ſome of them begin to fall) they will naturally ripen of themſelues. And whereas the Peares that are gathered, beeing through ripe, doe ſoone rot one another, through their ouer great heat: on the other ſide, the temperate heate of thoſe that bee gathered before they bee all full ripe, doth cauſe them to ripen one another.</p>
                  <p>But for Peares that are to be carryed any farre way, they muſt be gathered by another obſeruation: that is, pull one off the tree, and cut it in the middle, and if you finde that it be hollow about the coare, &amp; the kernell to haue roome, as it were looſening within the coare, although none of the Peares on that tree be ſo ripe as to drop off, then it hath his full grouth, and (although not then ful ripe, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be eaten) may be gathered. And hauing layde then vpon an heape, or one vpon an other, as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3634:7"/>they muſt be in the carriage, they wil in a very time ripen, &amp; eate as kindly as if they had been gathered ripe off the tree: but being gathered before this time, that is, before the time that they begin to be hollow about the coare, they will wither, ſhrinke, &amp; eate tough, more like in taſte to a peece of the tree, then a Peare.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Diuers wayes vſed in gathering of Peares.</head>
                  <p>KNow alſo that all kinde of Peares &amp; Apples are by diuers men, diuers waies vſed to bee handled, euen in the very manner of gathering them. As, ſome vſe to clime vp without a ladder, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a baſket to gather in, with alyne tyed to it, that thereby it may be let downe when it is full, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other vpon the grownd to receiue it, he in the tree ſtill holding the one end of the cord or lyne, that when the baſket is emptied, he may draw it vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: which way is not to be commended.</p>
                  <p>Other ſome with a ladder doe get vp, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a baſket in their hands, and euery time that it is full they bring it downe, powring the fruite into ſome other bigger baſket, not regarding either how they handle the fruit in the powring, nor how rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; boyſterouſly they place their ladder, to the hurt of the tree. Other ſome beate them downe with poles, breaking both the tree and fruite.</p>
                  <p>Theſe two laſt ſort of gatherers haue little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect what fruite may grow vpon the trees for the time enſuing, in regard of their rough handling of the tree, in breaking the boughes, ſprigs and bruts
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3634:7"/>whereupon fruite might growe. Onely for the time preſent is all their care: ſome being but tenants at will, or other careleſſe and ignorant perſons being put in truſt to gather.</p>
                  <p>But for the ſetting of your ladder to the tree, the beſt way is, to place it eaſily: For, laying of it hard on, will ſpoile &amp; fell a great many of the fruite, as far as the ladder toucheth. Alſo being firmely placed, it is both good for the gatherers owne ſafegard, and for the ſafegard of the tree. But, being careleſſe and raſh in placing thereof vpon the weake boughes &amp; branches, the weight of the gatherer to the tree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, will breake the weake branches &amp; endanger the gatherer.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="apples" type="fruit">
               <head>How to gather apples, and how to know when they are ready to be gathered.</head>
               <p>ANd touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gathering of apples, beginning firſt with ſommer fruite, as Ieniting apples, Margaret apples, ſo called in <hi>Kent,</hi> &amp; others which are too tedious in this place to be nominated: yet by the rules hereafter, although the fruits not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, ſhall you know their due ſeuerall times of gathering. If they haue their full grouth, ſome of the ripeſt will bee dropping off the tree, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the birds will be picking of them. Or els, you may pull off one of the greeneſt, cut it, &amp; if you finde that it is hollow about the coare, and the kirnell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to be looſe (as is ſhewed before in the tryal of Peares) then haue they their ful grouth, and they are ready to be gathered. And being gathered either of theſe waies, they will in the houſe come to their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3634:8"/>perfect colour, and ripen kindly of themſelues: but if they bee gathered afore, they will ſhrinke, wither, and eate tough, and doe no ſeruice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="winter fruit" type="fruit">
               <head>Winter fruite, how to be gathered.</head>
               <p>VVInter or laſting fruite, ſhould bee gathered in the wane of the Moone, the winde not being in the Eaſt: although indeed the Fruiterers of <hi>London</hi> by reaſon of their great quantity doe not obſerue the ſame. For, when they doe once begin to gather, they giue not ouer, vntill they haue gathered the laſt, except in foule or wet weather. For al fruite whatſoeuer being gathered in wet weather, or as long as the deaw hangs vpon the trees, be they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſo good laſting fruite, it will cauſe them in ſhort time to rot. For, being wet or moyſt when they bee gathered, ſoone after that they be houſed and layed, it will bring them into a heate, cauſing them to rot, and be mildeawed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="harvest_and_storage">
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How to vſe your gathering hooke.</head>
                  <p>AS concerning the better handling of your fruite in the gathering, the placing of the ladder hath been before ſpecified: you muſt alſo bee proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of a hooke and a gathering apron or bag. The hooke, to pul the bough that you cannot reach with your hand: The bagge or gathering apron, to put in your fruite, as you gather them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the gathering apron, and the manner how to faſten it about you.</head>
                  <p>THe gathering apron is commonly euery way
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3634:8"/>an Ell: hauing, at the lower end thereof, in the middeſt of the hemme, a ſtrong loope. Set this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pron about your back, knitting both the vpper ends afore, then take vp the loope-end (which hung downe) putting your girdle through the loope: and ſo hauing faſtened your girdle about you, tye the two corners of the loope end of your apron, the one of one ſide vnder your girdle, the other on the other ſide, doubling each of the corners vnder your gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, for feare of ſlipping: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your apron will be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for both your handes, or either of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to put in your fruite, as you gather it. And when your a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pron is full, looſe but one of the ends faſtened vnder your girdle: &amp; ſo bowing ſomewhat downe your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy on that ſide, let fall your fruite very tenderly into your prickell or baſket. For, in laying them downe roughly, their owne ſtalkes will pricke them. And, although then nothing ſeene or noted, yet they, that are ſtalke-prickt, will in time rot, beginning in the verie ſame place. But if you haue not ſuch aprons ready, then take a bagge of a buſhell, halfe a buſhell, or thereabout, with a wollen liſt or ſome ſuch like thing ſo broad, both endes ſowed to the bagges mouth, in length as might ſerue to hang vpon your ſhoulder &amp; reach your girdle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Fruite to be gathered, without bruts or leaues: and why.</head>
                  <p>GAther your fruite cleane (as neere as you can) without leafe or brut: onely gather it with the ſtalke. For, pulling any more then the ſtalke, breeds two diſcommodities: the one to the tree, the other to the fruite. To the tree, becauſe that the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3634:9"/>brut would, the next yeere, haue been growne to be a ſtalke whereupon the fruite might grow. To the fruite, becauſe the brut being gathered, and ioyned to the fruite with the ſtalke, will (in the powring of them downe) breake the next vnto it, although at that time not much ſeene: which will cauſe it to rot before his time. The leaues likewiſe, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, will in a ſhort time rot the fruite. And as the fruite is not to be gathered, but with the ſtalk onely, ſo is it not to bee gathered without a ſtalke. For, as the brut, as far as it toucheth, doth hurt the fruite: ſo, without the ſtalke, it will not laſt long, it will rot in the very ſtalke roome.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How to vſe your fallings.</head>
                  <p>THey that fall off the tree, which be not gathered with ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, are not to be layed with the reſt. For, commonly they are broken or bruiſed, with the fall: by reaſon whereof they will not laſt, and, being lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed amongſt the gathered fruite, will in time ſpoile them. Yet are thoſe fallings better, that fall when the fruite hath his full grouth, then they which fall before the time of gathering, as wind-falles, &amp; ſuch other. For they that fall before their full grouth wil ſhrinke, be withered, and neuer doe ſeruice: but they that are taken vp in gathering time, being layed by themſelues, will ſerue to roaſt or bake, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Abuſes, in gathering of fruite.</head>
                  <p>IN ſome great fruite countries, as <hi>Worceſter ſhire,</hi> and <hi>Gloceſter-ſhire,</hi> they vſe to beate downe their coorſe fruite, where of they make their Perry &amp; Cider, and likewiſe carry them in long carts, iog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3634:9"/>one againſt another, by reaſon of their looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in the cart, alſo in ſackes: which kinde of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, doth batter and bruiſe them: yet ſerue they for that purpoſe, or to ſpend or vſe out of the way: but the fruite, that is to bee reſerued for other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, is not ſo to be vſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How to carry the fruite after the gathering, in what baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, and how they ſhall be ſhot.</head>
                  <p>IF your fruite be gathered neere the place, where they are to bee layed vp, there muſt bee prouided certaine baſkets or prickles, (able to containe two buſhels, or a buſhell a peece) each of them hauing two eares or handles, that ſo (being full) they may be carryed, betweene two, holding each of them one of the handles, in their hands, or betwixt them to be carryed vpon a coule-ſtaffe, and ſo into the place appointed: by which meanes of carriage, the fruite will be neither bruiſed nor battered. Alſo haue a care, that they be poured or ſhot downe very gently, laying euery ſort by themſelues. But if there bee want of roome, hauing ſo many ſorts, that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not well lay them ſeuerall (for ſome haue diuers ſorts, although very ſmall ſtore of fruite) yet ſuch of ſummer-fruite as are neereſt, in taſte, &amp; colour, &amp; of winter fruite, ſuch as will taſte alike, may (if neede be) be layed together: and in time they may be ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, as hereafter ſhall bee expreſſed. But if the fruite be gathered, farre from whence they are to be layed, and that they muſt be carryed or conueyghed by cart or wagon (hauing any good ſtore to carry) there muſt be prouided great baſkets, or (as ſome call them) Maunds, of quarters or halfe quarters.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3634:10"/>And for the carriage, eſpecially of ſummer Peares, greene fearne muſt be vſed to lyne them withall, on the inſide of the Maunds: And here bee carefull to pul the ſtubborne ends of the fearne, cleane through the baſket, that ſo they may be on the out-ſide. By this meanes, neither ſhall the fearne ſlip to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, when the fruite is poured out into the maund, neither ſhall thoſe hard ends bruiſe the fruite. Alſo couer your maund cloſe with fearne: &amp; with a great packe-needle, bigger then ordinary packe-needles, draw a lyne or ſmall cord cloſing hard the fearne, that the fruite fall not out, neither be iogged or toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in carriage. The fearne doth not onely ſtand in the ſtead aforeſaid, but it cauſeth the peares ſoone to ripen (remaining any time therein) and to eate as well as if they had been gathered ripe: but if they be once come to a heate, and not taken out of the fearne in time, they will ſoone rot &amp; become blacke.</p>
                  <p>When you haue brought your peares to the place appointed, if at the looſing of them out of the maunds you finde them not ripe, if you will haſten the ripening of them, lay them thicke vpon fearne, and with fearne alſo couer them cloſe: for, being kept warme, they wil ſoone ripen and come to their perfect colour: alwaies prouided, that when they be neer ripe, they be vncouered. For, when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ripen, being kept cloſe, they will ripen too faſt: and being vncouered, at that time, the ayre wil moderate their heate. But if otherwiſe, you meane not to haſten the ripening of them, lay them vpon the bare boards, neither too thicke nor too thin, and they will leaſurely ripen.</p>
                  <p>For winter or laſting peares, they may be carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3634:10"/>and packed either in fearne or ſtrawe: not to the intent that the fearne ſhould haſten the ripening of them: but that in the carriage they may not be bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered. Alſo, at their iourneys end, they muſt be layed vpon fine ſweet ſtraw: prouided that they bee not layed in too warme a roome, leaſt ſo you bring them into a heate: neither layed in a windy colde roome, for feare of ſhrinking and riueling them: but in a roome indifferent, where they ſhall haue ayre, &amp; not too much.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How to gather Wardens.</head>
                  <p>VVArdens are to be carried, packt, and layed, as winter Peares.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How to gather Medlers, and how to keep them.</head>
                  <p>MEdlers are to be gathered about Michaelmas, after that a froſt hath touched them: at which time they are commonly in their full grouth, &amp; will be then dropping off the tree, but neuer ripe vpon the tree. And after they be gathered, they are to bee layed in a baſket, ſiue, barrell, or any ſuch like caſke, and wrapt about with wollen clothes, vnder, ouer, and on the ſides: alſo ſome waight layed vpon them, hauing a board betweene. For, except that they bee brought into a heate, they will neuer ripen kindely, nor eate well. And after they haue layen ſo long as you thinke, or finde, that any of them be ripe, (as they will not ripen all together) the ripeſt, ſtill as they ripen, muſt be taken from the reſt. Therefore poure them out into another ſiue, or baſket, leaſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that ſo you may well finde them, that bee ripeſt: letting the hard ones fal into this other baſket, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3634:11"/>thoſe that be ripe layed aſide, the other that be halfe ripe ſeuer alſo in a third baſket or ſiue. For, if they that be ripe, or halfe ripe, be not ſeperated from the other, the one will bee mouldy before the other bee ripe, and ſo ſpoile the reſt. And ſtill after that the ripeſt are taken from the other, they are fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time to be vſed as aforeſaid, vntill that they bee all ripe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How to order Quinces.</head>
                  <p>QVinces are a fruite, which, if there be any ſtore of them, be not to be layed in that roome, where any other fruite is, by reaſon of their ſtrong ſent. For, being layed in any cloſe roome, neer other fruit, it will cauſe the fruite to ſmell of them. The riper alſo that they be, the ſtronger their ſent is: eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if they be in a cloſe roome: and they will not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be hurtfull to the fruite neere them, but noyſome alſo to them that come into the roome where they bee. Therefore they are to bee layed, in ſuch a roome ſeuerall (vpon fine ſtraw) where they ſhall haue ayre enough. Alſo, being to be carryed any far way, they muſt bee packt in ſtraw: and ſo likewiſe Medlers. Their time of gathering alſo is all one with Medlers.</p>
                  <p>As the order of packing, &amp; vſage of Peares, Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, &amp; Quinces is ſhewed: ſo likewiſe ſhall bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the manner of packing pippins, and al other ſorts of apples, beginning with the ſummer fruite.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How to packe or maunde apples.</head>
                  <p>ALL kinde of ſummer or winter apples muſt be packt, layed, and carryed in wheate or rather
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3634:11"/>rye ſtraw. And although, for the moſt part, they are layed in ſome roome, neere where they growe, vntill they be all gathered &amp; ready to be carryed away: yet the better way for thoſe that are to conueigh their fruite, from whence they are gathered, is to haue maunds, ſtraw, &amp; all ready, lyning them with ſtraw, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your baſkets or prickels be ful, you may preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly poure them into the maunds. For, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firſt layed in one place, and then taken vp again, to be put into maunds or other caſks, doth hurt the fruite with too much toſſing: but being preſently put into the maunds, well packt, and gently hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, will cauſe ſummer fruite to keep plumpe, &amp; keep their colour the better.</p>
                  <p>If you haue not ſo many of one kinde of fruite, or that there be a remnant (as of ſome ſorts, there bee but a fewe, in an orchard) ſo that the maund cannot be filled: firſt poure in one ſort, and when they bee all in, lay ſome fine ſweet ſtrawe vpon them, then poure in the other kinde of fruite, and ſo fill your maunde: and being filled and well packt, the two ſorts will not come together in the ſtirring or car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How to empty maunds, and how to lay the fruite.</head>
                  <p>AT the emptying of them, ſee that the fruite bee not raſhly poured out, leaſt that the ſeuerall ſorts com together. And although packt and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed in ſtraw, yet at the emptying let the ſtraw bee pickt out cleane: and, as neere as you can, let euery ſort be layed ſeuerall. Now, if there bee ſo many ſorts, that, for want of roome, ſome of them muſt be mixed, be ſure that you mingle none, but thoſe that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3634:12"/>will laſt alike: But if they bee neere in taſte and colour, there needes no ſeparation. But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſome ſortes doe laſt alike, and be neere of one taſte, yet if they be not of a colour, they are not to be layed together. For, it is an vnſeemely ſight to ſee one heape of apples of ſeuerall colours. But if already they be mingled, let them be taken vp with a Trey: and looke how many ſorts there be in the heape, you muſt haue by you ſo many baſkets, and ſo part euery ſort, ſeuerall: when they be parted, the ripeſt to be firſt ſpent, &amp; the reſt by degrees in their time.</p>
                  <p>And although they that be ſummer fruite, be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led rathe fruite, yet are they not ripe all at one time. Wherfore, no ſorts muſt belayed together, but thoſe that ripen alike: otherwiſe, being layed together in a heape, the one will be rotten before the other bee ripe, and cauſe the hardeſt amongſt them to rot, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be kindely ripe.</p>
                  <p>Alſo Pippins and other winter fruite, are to bee carryed and packt in maunds, lyned with wheate or rye ſtraw: and at the emptying of them, the ſtraw to be cleane pickt out. And when your pippins, or other winter fruite, come to be layed in the houſe or place appointed, whether they ſhould be conueighed or carryed, vnlace your maunds, take off the ſtraw, at the top: when you haue done, whelme downe the maunds, emptying them gently, into ſmall baſkets, picking out the ſtraw as cleane as you can. Haue a great care alſo in ſhooting or pouring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out. For, in pouring of them hard, the one wil hurt the other: eſpecially the ſtalkes of the one, will run into the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And being once ſtalk-prickt, they will not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3634:12"/>laſt long, although not preſently ſeene.</p>
                  <p>Alſo, being battered or bruiſed, they cannot keep. Onely the Pippin hath a qualitie by it ſelfe. For, if it be battered, the ſkinne being not broken, it will dry vp againe: ſo that it be when it is greene, and being layed amongſt the reſt: for then they will ſoake away the bruiſe, and make it plumpe againe, if it be not too much bruiſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the difference of fruite, growing in one ground, and on one tree.</head>
                  <p>YOu muſt note that there be pippins and other winter fruite, although of one ſort, and grow in one ground or orchard, that will laſt better then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome: and of ſome trees growe greater fruite the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of other ſome of the ſame ſort, &amp; in the very ſame orchard. For, where the ſunne hath moſt power or ſhineth hotteſt, the fruite is harder grained, bigger, and of a better colour, then they that grow vpon the very ſame tree, vpon the lower boughes (which are called water boughes) or the inner boughes of the tree. For, the raine or moyſture that lights vpon the tree, falles to the lower parts: by reaſon wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they neuer haue any good colour, but are alwaies greene and ſoft, and eate very wateriſh: which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them, they can neuer laſt long, nor eat kindely. But the other (as I ſaid) that haue the warmth of the ſunne, doe grow greater and better coloured: ſome being red ſided, other ſome ruſſet: alſo they laſt long and eate kindly.</p>
                  <p>Therefore I wiſh them, that haue fine laſting fruite, that they make great ſtore of, for the ſeruice
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3634:13"/>of their owne houſe, to ſeparate them at the gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. But otherwiſe, if they bee ſuch fruite, that no ſuch account is to be made of them, they may belay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed altogether: and after that they haue layen, take them vp in a trey, and ſeparate the ripeſt from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo ſpend them as occaſion ſerues.</p>
                  <p>Alſo, the largeneſſe, &amp; goodnes of the fruite, holds proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the age of the tree. For, while y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tree is in growing to perfection, the fruite groweth eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry yeere bigger and bigger, better in taſte, &amp; colour, &amp; more firme and hard: but when the tree begins to decay &amp; waxe olde, the fruite (which it beareth) doth alſo decay in bignes, colour, taſte &amp; firmenes: &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently will not laſt ſo long.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How to order fruite, in conueighing them by water.</head>
                  <p>IF there bee any occaſion of ſending fruite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny farre way by water, eſpecially ſuch fine fruite, that will keep well, and worth ſending (for ſummer fruit are not farre to be ſent) prouide ſome dry hogſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, barrels, or ſome ſuch caſke, and becauſe they may lye the cloſer (to auoide iogging and toſſing, in remoouing or ſtirring of the caſke) they muſt be lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in, by hand, one by one: not poured in. For, being poured in, they will lye hollow, &amp; ſo be ſpoiled with battering, and bruiſing one againſt another, in the remouing of the caſke: but, being layed in, one by one, and the caſke filled vp, they will not ſtirre.</p>
                  <p>Lyne your caſkes at both ends, with the fineſt &amp; ſweeteſt ſtraw, you can get: but not the ſides of your caſke: for too much warmth will hurt them. You muſt alſo pearce holes in both ends, about eight or ten at an end. For, fruite (let them be euer ſuch good
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3634:13"/>laſting fruite) if they haue not ayre, they will quickly come in a great heate, and ſo ſodainly rot. Haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a great care that they be kept dry in the cariage. For, as the want of ayre doth cauſe them to rot: ſo, being wet will rot them likewiſe.</p>
                  <p>Alſo fruite, that are to be carryed by ſea, may bee ſhot vnder hatches vpon ſtraw, if there be not caſke enough to carry them in. Alwayes prouided, that they be ſhot in a dry place, and with great care that they be kept dry ouer head: now and then opening the hatches to ayre them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Vnfit times to remoue or carry fruite, by land or water: and the reaſon thereof.</head>
                  <p>THe fruite that is ſtirred, packt, or carryed in froſty weather, or in March (if the winde blow ſharp) let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be euer ſo hard at the taking vp, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they come to their iourneys end, being carried by land or water, they wil then be ſo te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der (in froſty weather, by reaſon of the colde ayre: in March, by reaſon of the ſharpe and bitter winde: and in ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, by reaſon of heate) that the moſt part of them will change blacke, and a great many of them ſo ſhriueld as if they had been ſodden: ſo that they wil not abide to be toſſed, nor carryed at that time of the yeare, by reaſon of their tendernes. The hardeſt &amp; the beſt laſting fruite, that is, after they haue layen long, or eſpecially if they haue layen till March, or neere the Spring, and ſo likewiſe vntill Iuly, the weather growing hotter &amp; hotter, although in the taking vp of them they ſeeme very hard, yet ſhal you finde a great alteration in them, after their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:3634:14"/>
                  <head>Small ſtore of fruite, how to be conueighed by land.</head>
                  <p>THey that haue but ſmall ſtore to carry, or but now and then to carry ſome, of what ſort ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, they doe commonly carry them in doſſers, pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niers, or prickles, &amp;c. one, on each ſide of the horſe: alwaies prouided, that euery or each one be full, the cherries &amp; peares to be lyned with greene fearne, al kinde of apples to be lyned with fine ſweet ſtrawe, onely in the bottome and top (not on the ſides) of the panniers and doſſers. But baſkets or prickles (the rods whereof are not ſo neere together) muſt be lyned, ſides and all.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>In what kinde of roomes, winter-fruite are to be layed, and in what manner.</head>
                  <p>FOr the better reſeruing or keeping of winter-fruite, firſt there muſt be great heede taken, what place or roome they are layed in: for it muſt be ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too hot nor too colde, neither too cloſe nor too open. For, as the cloſenes of the roome brings the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a great heate, ſo doth too much ayre make them ſhrinke, and be withered: beſides, in time of yeare, the froſt will ſore nip them. You muſt alſo haue a great care, that they be neither layed vpon the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, in any low roome, or cellar: vnles it be either paued or boarded. For, although they be vnderlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed well with ſtrawe, yet the moyſtnes of the bare ground wil cauſe the ſtraw to be muſtie, &amp; the muſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes aſcend to the fruite: which wil make them both muſty and mouldy.</p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:3634:14"/>
                  <p>The laying of fruite in a lowe roome or cellar (ſo that the roome be ſweet, and eyther boorded or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, being not very cloſe) is good, from Chriſtmas vntill the latter end of March: which will both keepe them from the froſt, and from the ſharpnes of the March winde. Betweene March and the latter end of May (being the chiefe of the ſpring) the cellars be hot: and, in that time, the fruite will run out, or rot, more in thoſe roomes, then in other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient places. Roomes, that be very ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are neither good for winter nor ſummer: and eſpecially ſuch as are neere the tyles where no ſeeling is ouer them. For, in winter, the ſharp windes and froſts wil haue acceſſe through the chinkes or creuiſſes of the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, although ſhut: and, betwixt the tiles, the heate of the ſunne, in hot weather will pearce like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. As cellars be hot toward the ſpring, they be cold in ſummer: and are then good to keep fruite in.</p>
                  <p>Roomes, that be ſeeled ouer head, are good for fruite, hauing ayre ſufficient, where the windowes may be ſhut and opened, as occaſion ſerueth. For, being ſeeled it will keep away duſt, that might haue fallen downe, and the heate of the ſunne. Alwayes prouided, in what roome ſoeuer, that they be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed, with good, cleane, and ſweet ſtrawe, eyther wheate or rye. Take alſo the longeſt of the ſtraw, and let it be layed to the walles, ſtanding vp as far as the fruite reacheth: not thicke, but onely ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to keep the fruite from the wall. Which, if it be a ſtone wall, will giue, at euery change of the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. If any other wall, it wil be ful of duſt. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſtraw is good, both to dry vp the moyſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes before it comes to the fruite, and likewiſe to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3634:15"/>keep away the duſt.</p>
                  <p>But if the roome bee eyther wayne-ſcotted or boarded round, there needs no ſtraw, betweene the walles and the fruite.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How winter-fruites, of one ſort and kinde, are to be culled, and ſorted diuerſly.</head>
                  <p>AS it is ſhewed how Summer-fruite (that is, ſuch as be rathe fruite, and to be ſpent in ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer) are to be ordered: ſo now ſhall be ſhewed, how winter or laſting fruite ſhall be vſed, and kept in their kinde, for their beſt laſting. And as there be diuers kindes of fruite that will not laſt, but muſt be vſed in ſummer, ſome at one time and ſome at another: ſo likewiſe there are diuers ſorts, which will naturally laſt, ſome but til Alhollantide, ſome till Chriſtmas, ſome till Landlemas, &amp; other ſome till Shrouetide, &amp;c. But eſpecially, Pippins, Iohn apples, or as ſome call them Dewzins, Pear-maynes, winter-ruſſettings, and ſuch other laſting ſeruiceable fruite, with good vſage, will laſt till new fruite come in.</p>
                  <p>It is the order in <hi>Kent,</hi> and in moſt fruite coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes in <hi>England,</hi> when they haue great heapes of fruite, lying in their houſes, to take a long rod or ſtaffe, with a nayle, or ſome ſuch ſharpe poynted thing, in the end thereof, and with the ſame to take vp thoſe they ſee rotten, vpon the top or ſide of the heapes: not regarding how they rot vndermoſt, and in the heart of the heape: where, is more waſte, then in the outward parts. And other ſome neuer ſtirre them, but when they haue occaſion to vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3634:15"/>and then taking them vp, and throwing out the rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ones, doe let the reſt rot that will.</p>
                  <p>But if you haue any fruit, that you meane to keep or reſerue, as long as they can, by their ſeuerall naturall kindes, they muſt be vſed in another ſort. When there is ſeene any periſht fruite, eyther vpon the toppe or ſides of your heape, then it ſheweth that ſome are rotten in the inner parts. Therfore, hauing a trey, with the ſame gently take them vp, being carefull, that you neither thruſt the trey hard to the heape, nor with your nayles touch them. And heere know, that although the fruite of your heape be all of one kinde, yet at the turning or taking vp of them, they are to bee parted into three ſorts: for they will not keep alike, although they grew all vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one tree. Therefore your trey being filled ſet it before you, with your prickles or baſkets round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you, &amp; taking them out of the trey, peruſe them well, and lay the hardeſt, or thoſe that are without ſpots, which will laſt longeſt, in the baſket next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, laying them downe gently: the other ſort that are broken ſkinned, ſtalke-pricked, or vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run (that is beginning to periſh) will be as good for the preſent time to ſpend, and as ſound as the other ſort, ſo that they be taken in time. For, when they begin once to be ſpotted, or any way the ſkinne bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, if it be but the breadth of a pins head, they will not laſt long. This ſecond ſort you muſt put into the ſecond prickle or baſket. The third ſort (for your third baſket) are thoſe that are already periſht, or worme eaten: which muſt be layed by themſelues ſeuerall, and ſpent out of hand: and thoſe that are
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3634:16"/>found throughly rotten, to bee caſt out, which will be but a fewe, if they be carefully looked into, ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or pouring euery ſort ſeuerall: and alwayes as they are turning, to bee vnderlayed with freſh &amp; ſweet ſtraw. But if they be not taken vp, &amp; loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to in time, you ſhal haue them, that be but ſtalk-prickt, or any way broken ſkind, ſoone rotten: and the other that be but a little periſht, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe other begin to periſh, wil be all rotten, and ſo ſpoile them, that would laſt long.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The times when long laſting fruite, ſhould be ſtirred and turned.</head>
                  <p>PIppins, Iohn-apples, Peare-maines, and other ſuch long laſting fruite, need not to bee turned, vntill the weeke before Chriſtmas, except that there bee ſome riper kinde of fruite mingled with them (which muſt be taken out) or that the fallings haue not been taken out at the gathering, or any ſtrawe left amongſt them.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond time, that you ſhould turne theſe laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kindes of fruite, is about Shrouetide, or the latter end of March, or the beginning of Aprill. For, towards the ſpring all kinds of fruite will rot, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at other times. And ſo vntill Whitſontide turne them once in the month, and afterwards once in a fortnight. Still, in the turning, lay your heape lower and lower, and your ſtraw vnderneath them very thinne. Alwaies prouided, that you doe not touch your fruite, in any great froſt, and eſpecially if they bee in an open roome. In a cellar or cloſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3634:16"/>roome, where the froſt cannot come at them, they may be touched, if there be any occaſion of haſte (or elſe not,) ſo that you keepe the roome very cloſe ſhut too, when they be in turning.</p>
                  <p>At the thaw, the fruite is wet and moyſt: and as long as they be ſo, they muſt not be touched, nor any way ſtirred, vntill that they be dry againe. And ſo likewiſe in rainy weather, they will be danke and moyſte, and giue, according to the weather: at which times they may not be touched. For, being touched in any of thoſe times aforeſayd, they wil turn black: and hauing once changed colour, they will not laſt. Therefore in what roome ſoeuer you lay them, ſet open your windows, doores, or other entrances for ayre (that ſo the winde may come in vpon them) in winter, betwixt nine in the forenoone, and foure in the afternoone: and in ſummer you may open at ſixe in the morning vntill eight at night. For, before and after theſe times, the ayre is too colde. In March open not your windowes at all: for the March winde will cauſe the fruite to ſhrinke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>When Pippins, and other long laſting fruite, begin to be ſhriueled: and the reaſon.</head>
                  <p>LAſting fruite, after that the middle of May is paſt, begin to wither: by reaſon that then they waxe dryer. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the moyſture being gone, which cauſed them to keep plumpe, they looke wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and become ſmaller. Alſo when nature is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3634:17"/>decayed in them (doe what you can) they will rot. For, in the Spring, as the tree yeelds fruit, ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and budding euery day more and more: ſo, doe the kirnels of the olde fruite, at that time, begin to ſwell &amp; ſprout within: and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it makes way at the ſtalke, and there begins for the moſt part to rot.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="erratum">
            <head>A fault eſcaped.</head>
            <p>Pag. 8. lyne 1. For, very time: Read, very ſhort time.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
